A Guide to the George Washington Letters, 1779-1796
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
George Washington Letters, 1779-1796
The Library of Virginia
24147
22 leaves, negative photostats
George Washington
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Purchased, April 1954, from Mary Garland of Richmond, Virginia.
Biographical Information
George Washington was born 22 February 1732 (adjusted calendar) in Westmoreland County, Virginia, to Augustine Washington (1694-1743) and Mary Ball Washington (1708-1789). He became a surveyor at a young age, and an officer in the Virginia militia. Washington was appointed a lieutenant colonel in the Virginia militia during the French and Indian War. He was a member of the House of Burgesses from 1758 to 1774, and a member of the first and second Continental Congresses in 1774 and 1775. On 15 June 1775, Washington was appointed General commanding the Continental Army and served until 1783. He was president of the Federal Constitutional Convention in 1787, and was elected the first president of the United States, serving from 1789 to 1797. He married Martha Dandridge Custis (1731-1802) 6 January 1759. Washington died at Mount Vernon in Fairfax County, Virginia, 14 December 1799, and was buried there
Scope and Content
Letters, 1779-1796, from George Washington (1732-1799) to Henry Lee (1756-1818) concerning military matters relating to Lee's command and its monitoring of British movements; expressing Washington's desire to improve communication and transportation routes between the Atlantic coast and western settlers; stating Washington's disinclination to have portraits painted; concerning Washington's interest in a threshing machine; and discussing political concerns. Also includes an address to Washington from the citizens of Alexandria, Virginia, on his election to the presidency.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Location of Originals
Originals are located at the Virginia Historical Society, Richmond, Virginia.
Contents List
- Letter, 30 October 1779, from Washington at headquarters at West Point, New York, informing Lee that the British have evacuated Rhode Island and General Horatio Gates had moved in.
- Letter, 13 April 1780, from Washington at headquarters at Morristown, New Jersey, regretting the necessary delay of Lee's Legion moving caused by problems with equipment and horses, also discussing a court martial with Lee.
- Letter, 28 June 1780, from Washington at headquarters at Ramapough, New Jersey, asking Lee to gather information on the enemy.
- Letter, 11 July 1780, from Washington at headquarters telling Lee to get necessary supplies and livestock and to give owners certificates.
- Letter, 19 July 1780, from Washington at headquarters telling Lee to keep an eye on the British fleet.
- Letter, 24 July 1780, from Washington at headquarters ordering Lee to take horses within Monmouth County, New Jersey for use by the Continental Army.
- Letter, 5 August 1780, from Washington at headquarters at Peekskill, New York, providing orders to Lee.
- Letter, 18 June 1786, from Washington at Mount Vernon, Fairfax County, Virginia to Lee concerning a shipment of books and stating Washington's belief in the necessity of improving transportation routes between the Atlantic coast and western settlers.
- Letter, 14 March 1789, from Washington at Mount Vernon thanking Lee for his letter.
- Address, April 1789, from the people of Alexandria, Virginia, congratulating Washington on his election to the presidency.
- Letter, 3 July 1792, from Washington in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, concerning having his portrait painted.
- Letter, 16 October 1793, from Washington at Mount Vernon concerning a threshing machine and expressing fear that opponents of the general government were trying to damage it.
- Letter, 11 January 1796, from Washington in Philadelphia concerning appointments of a chief justice and cabinet positions.